<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from a gentleman of the Lord Ambassador Howard's retinue, to his friend in London dated at Fez, Nov. 1, 1669 wherein he gives a full relation of the most remarkable passages in their voyage thither, and of the present state of the countries under the power of Taffaletta, emperour of Morocco : with a brief account of the merchandizing commodities of Africa : as also the manners and customs of the people there.</title>
            <author>S. L., Gentleman of the Lord Ambassador Howard's retinue.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 74 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L61</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5130</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13483690</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13483690</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99716</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99716)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 461:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from a gentleman of the Lord Ambassador Howard's retinue, to his friend in London dated at Fez, Nov. 1, 1669 wherein he gives a full relation of the most remarkable passages in their voyage thither, and of the present state of the countries under the power of Taffaletta, emperour of Morocco : with a brief account of the merchandizing commodities of Africa : as also the manners and customs of the people there.</title>
                  <author>S. L., Gentleman of the Lord Ambassador Howard's retinue.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. G.for Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 31: S. L.</note>
                  <note>Addressed on p. 1: To his very loving friend T. G. in London.</note>
                  <note>"A brief account of the native commodities of Africa" with caption title on p. 33.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Africa --  Description and travel.</term>
               <term>Morocco --  Description and travel.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:99716:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
A LETTER From a Gentleman of the Lord Ambaſſador <hi>HOWARD</hi>'s Retinue, To his Friend in <hi>London:</hi> Dated at <hi>FEZ,</hi> Nov. 1. 1669.</p>
            <p>Wherein he gives a full Relation of the moſt Remarkable Paſſages in their Voyage thither, and of the preſent State of the Countries under the Power of <hi>TAFFALETTA,</hi> Emperour of <hi>MOROCCO;</hi> With a brief account of the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing Commodities of <hi>AFRICA;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo, The Manners and Cuſtoms of the People there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed for Publick ſatisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G.</hi> for <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>White Hart</hi> in <hi>Little Britain,</hi> Anno Dom. 1670.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99716:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99716:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To his very Loving Friend</hi> T. G. <hi>in</hi> LONDON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ccording to your earneſt Requeſt, you have here a full Account of the Eſtate of this Country, as much as I have received from very good hands. I wiſh that it may give you that ſatisfaction that you requeſt. It is certain that all that have written any thing of <hi>Africa,</hi> have ſpoken of it as blind Men of Colours, by gueſs, and by hearſay. The Truth is ſo mixed with Fables and Tales, that it is not eaſie to diſtinguiſh them. This Part of <hi>Africa</hi> is much changed within theſe two hundred years, and the Names of Places and People altered; ſo that we ſhall loſe our labour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the ancient Writers, concerning the preſent condition of this Country. It might give great ſatisfaction to the Learned in the Northern Climates, to be informed of all the Tranſactions of this unknown World, but that we can never expect whilſt Trading is ſo much neglected here and Strangers, eſpecially Chriſtians, do run ſo many hazards when they enter into the Land; it being one of the Articles of the <hi>Moors</hi> Faith, that he that ſheds Chriſtian Blood in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99716:3"/>
their <hi>Ramedam,</hi> merits Heaven, and purchaſes the Eternal Favour of God with this Sacrifice: So great an invitation to Cruelty, may juſtly ſtop us, that are not weary of our Lives, from running too far amongſt them, unleſs it be upon a good account of Trading or Peace, and then none dares expoſe himſelf alone to the Peoples mercy without ſufficient guard to defend him; yet I have ſeen ſome <hi>French</hi> Merchants riding abroad without fear, and return ſafely: I conceive they were known to the People, who are ſenſible that the acquaintance with forreign Nations, is very neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for their more convenient ſubſiſtance.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> are to be ſeen every where in this Country, they are very ſerviceable to the Inhabitants, for they furniſh them for the moſt part with forreign Commodities, and make thoſe things that are neceſſary for them. They never grow rich, but the <hi>Mahumetans</hi> do accuſe them of ſome Crime, to have a pretence to ſeize upon their Treaſure, as it happened lately to a <hi>Jew,</hi> who was grown a petty Prince; he Commanded a Place ſtrong by Situation and Art, called <hi>Darbinmeſhaal,</hi> there was but one aſcent, and that ſo diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, that without his leave all the <hi>Moors</hi> of <hi>Barbary</hi> might have ſpent their daies in the Siege of it; for beſides that it is impregnable, it contains ſo much ground within the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain as might very well nouriſh a thouſand head of Cattle, and ſupply them with Corn and Fodder. This <hi>Jew</hi> had won the eſteem and favour of the Grandees round about by his courteous behaviour and good hoſpitality; for it was his cuſtom to invite all the Perſons of Note into his City, and there entertain them very kindly: This dealing made every one, eſpecially the <hi>Arabs,</hi> to love him, and got him a great Name. When <hi>Muley Archeid,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Taffaletta,</hi> flung himſelf into the protection of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> and that they had all owned him for their Prince, he was alſo entertained by this courteous <hi>Jew,</hi> and at a ſmall provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he was inaſſacred: <hi>Taffaletta</hi> found one Point in the Law of <hi>Mahomet</hi> to juſtifie the Murder, which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99716:3"/>
of, and applauded by the ignorant Multitude. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother <hi>Jew</hi> named <hi>Joſeph Ben-ſimon,</hi> a very great Trader, and one that had Correſpondents in many Places, did run the ſame Fortune. He ſupplyed the <hi>Moors</hi> with many Commodities, eſpecially with Powder and Shot, Guns and other Weapons, which he conveyed out of <hi>Spain</hi> by ſtealth. At laſt his Wealth made him guilty of Death, for he was accuſed of Adultery, and although common report pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced him innocent, he loſt his Life, and had his Eſtate ſeized for the Kings Uſe. Thus all the Princes of theſe Countries do treat this miſerable Nation. When they have occaſion for Money, they force it from the <hi>Jews,</hi> either by right or wrong. <hi>Gayland,</hi> as I am informed, did enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Arzilla,</hi> for no other end but to have ſome on whom he might prey: He raiſed a conſiderable Sum of Money from them on this occaſion: About thirty or forty Families of the <hi>Jews</hi> had managed all the Trade of that part of the Country, and were grown rich; <hi>Gayland</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults his <hi>Cadir,</hi> and asks from this deceitful Oracle, whether it was lawful to ſuffer <hi>Jews,</hi> Infidels, to dwell amongſt the <hi>Muſulmans?</hi> He anſwered, That it was not lawful, but that if they would not turn <hi>Mahometans,</hi> he was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Law of <hi>Mahomet</hi> to puniſh that contempt with preſent Death. This ſad News frighted the <hi>Jews,</hi> eſpecially when they heard that the day was appointed for their Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; in the mean whiles they Petition the Sultan, and make their Peace by offering a large ſum of Money, all they had gathered in many years. This ſatisfied <hi>Gayland</hi>'s weak Conſcience, concerning the bloody clauſe of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> Law, and made him free them from the great danger that threatened them. You ſee by that what favour Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers may expect from this treacherous People.</p>
            <p>But before I begin to inform you of my Journey from <hi>Tangier,</hi> and of the Eſtate of this Count<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, I will relate unto you ſomething of our Paſſage thither<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Garriſon: You may know many Particulars from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99716:4"/>
them that have dwelt there ſome years; but from very few you may learn what I have obſerv'd in that Place: Some things I have taken notice of, which if they were well known in <hi>England,</hi> and minded, might make it a happy City.</p>
            <p>At our departure from <hi>England,</hi> we ſailed near the <hi>Sylly</hi> Iſlands, where we met with a North-weſt Wind that blew very freſh a day and a night; we made ſuch Advantage of it, that in that time we were carried near 80 Leagues from the Lands End, into the Bay of <hi>Biſcay;</hi> a moſt dreadful Sea, at the leaſt breath of Wind the Waves ſwell into Mountains: It is a grievous thing to be toſt in this Sea by a Tempeſt: The danger is able to try the ſtouteſt Courage. I know it by our Paſſage over this Place, the wind began to turn about, and then we heard that doleful Cry of the Seamen, <hi>No Near</hi> That begat in us a longing to ſee the pleaſant Shore; but we were not long before the wind favoured us again, which did ſometimes toſs us till we were come near the Coaſt of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> where we met with theſe Particulars that I cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit:</p>
            <p>In a lovely calm Morning, as the Sun began to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and viſit us with his Beams, the Air being clear, and the Weather moſt pleaſant, we ſpied a Face of a Riſing of the Water; the Seamen called it a Spout: I know no other Name for it, unleſs I call it the greateſt Miracle in Nature; The Figure was like a Pyramide, ſharp at the top, and large at the bottom, about the compaſs of two or three Acres of Ground; the Top reach'd ſo high, that I could not well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it: I wondred at the ſight, ſo did many of the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who profeſſed to have never ſeen the like in the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Parts. I admired from whence ſuch a Violence in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could proceed; That the Water ſhould leave its own Element, and aſcend up into the Air, and in ſuch great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, it is not poſſible without ſome moſt powerful Agent: I began to reaſon with ſome who eſteem themſelves of the more refined Souls, and to ask their Judgment about it; but<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99716:4"/>
I found their Anſwers ſo dull and impertinent, that I quickly diſcovered their ignorance. We ſailed within two Leagues of the Place, and had time to behold it at our leiſure; as we approached nearer, we found a Current turning that way, which, if we had ventured farther, might have endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered our Lives; but the wind being pretty freſh, and all our Sails open, the Current at ſuch a diſtance, could not prevail upon us. One thing we took notice of, which ſeem'd very wonderful; out of the Pyramid of Waters about a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Yards high, leapt ſomething that was Bulky; for it made a Plunge in the Water, that appear'd to us, we imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be a Fiſh of a conſiderable Bigneſs, which the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Aſcent of the water had ſent up in the Air, but then meeting with a leſſer and a weaker motion, at a diſtance from the Sea, it had the power to free it ſelf from that Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity from which it was hurried, by caſting it ſelf again into the Ocean. This happened ſeveral times, whether it was the ſame Fiſh, we could not well diſtinguiſh: This Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may ſeem very incredible, but you may have it confirmed by many that venture to the <hi>Indies,</hi> who do often meet upon the Coaſt of <hi>Guiny</hi> with ſuch Wonders of Nature.</p>
            <p>Immediatly after this ſtrange ſight, we felt the Wind more violent, and ſaw the Air darken, and fill'd with many threatning Clouds; therefore we prepared for a ſtorm, which did quickly overtake us to our great advantage; for it drave us with ſuch violence, that we made ſix Leagues in an hour with our Main Sail ſpread: All that day it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, and was accompanied with ſuch grievous Rain that I never ſavv the like in <hi>England:</hi> It vvas fearful to us that had never expoſed our Lives to the Mercy of the Liquid E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement, eſpecially vvhen vve felt our ſhip crack under us, and the main Maſt bend as a Bovv. But the Evening deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered us from all fear; for then a handſom Gale of Wind ſucceeded the Tempeſt, and diſperſed all the fearful Clouds that did ſurround us, and the ſetting Sun took his leave of us with a pleaſant countenance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99716:5"/>
The next day we ſaw afar off a Whale ſpouting Water in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Air very high for its Paſtime: And about forty Leagues off on this ſide of the Southern Cape, we beheld two Veſſels chaſing one another; the Wind being North-weſt, and they making towards the Land, we could only diſcover their Colours; the one was a <hi>Turks</hi> Man of War, the other a <hi>Hamburger;</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> overtook his Enemy, and then began a furious Fight, which laſted about two hours; the Guns did thunder on both ſides, to our ſatisfaction that were not engaged in the Peril: We could not diſcover how they ended their Quarrel, becauſe the Chriſtian Ship main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a running Fight, and made with all Sail towards the ſhore.</p>
            <p>The next morning we had a ſight of the Cape St. <hi>Vincent,</hi> otherwiſe the Southern Cape, a noted place to all ſtrangers; we were not long ignorant of the Maritine Cuſtoms of that Place, which were ſignified unto us by the Ship-Company, that demanded their uſual Fees from all that had never been there before. Ile aſſure you, Sir, the Joy that we did feel at ſuch a ſight, to be ſo happily eſcaped out of the danger of the Sea, made us be liberal of our Purſes, and of our ſtrong Drink; for we were not far from <hi>Tangier,</hi> our Landing-Place, which the next day we diſcovered, and were moſt joyfully received by the Governour and Inhabitants, that cauſed the Eleven Guns of the Town to proclaim our Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val.</p>
            <p>Before I go from hence, I will give you a ſhort Account of this Renowned City. It is ſituate upon the Decline of a Hill; the Houſes are ſo built, that from moſt you have a pleaſant Proſpect into the <hi>Straights Mouth:</hi> It is almoſt triangular, and ſtretches it ſelf along the Sea ſhore: A high Hill overlooks the Town on the North-ſide, where a ſtrong Caſtle is built capacious enough to hold a thouſand or two thouſand men in Garriſon. <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal</hi> fortified it with high Baſtions of ſquare Stone: Over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt there is a large Bay, where, ſome ſay, Coral is to be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99716:5"/>
found. Round about on the Land-ſide ſeveral little Hills do ſtand that are now fortified with Lines and Forts for fear of the Enemy. A conſiderable Compaſs of Ground is enclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within the outtermoſt Lines. I had the curioſity to take a view of every part of the Town, and its Dependencies. An Officer of my Acquaintance, Mr. <hi>T.</hi> by name, offered himſelf to ſatisfie me: We entred firſt into the Caſtle, and there I took notice of many Stones that did bear the Names of thoſe that governed that Province in the time of the <hi>Romans;</hi> theſe were fixed in the Wall of the Governors Houſe. Out of the Caſtle I found an old ruined Building, almoſt all buried in its own Rubbiſh: A little farther, ſome ancient Graves cut out of the hard Rock, about four foot broad, and nine in length; by which I diſcovered the great diminution in the ſtature of men, that are nothing near ſo large and ſo high as in primitive times, Nature ſtill falls into Decay. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> of <hi>Andaluzia</hi> are the leaſt men I have ever ſeen; our Boys of twelve years old are higher. I took notice alſo thereby of the great care the Ancients had to preſerve their Dead Bodies and Aſhes from being diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and diſperſed, which doubtleſs did proceed from their Belief of a Reſurrection. We continued our Walk farther into the Fields, and there I had an excellent Proſpect over all the Works and Forts built by that great Captain for whom <hi>Tangier</hi> may ever mourn; I mean the Renowned Earl of <hi>Tiveot.</hi> My Friend related unto me his unhappy Death, and ſhewed me beſides, the Wood in which he was kill'd in the company of 600 ſtout men, with moſt of the Officers of the Garriſon. He was a man of great experience in Martial Affairs, having done ſo good ſervice in the <hi>French</hi> Wars, that <hi>Mazarine</hi> appointed unto him during his Life a yearly Penſion. The occaſion of his Misfortune was this; He had ſent into <hi>Portugal</hi> for Lime and Materials for the Fortifications: The Ships being not yet arrived, and that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Men that came from the Guard, wanting imployment, he reſolved to make ſome execution with them upon a Wood
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99716:6"/>
that did ſerve as a Retreat unto ſome ſtragling <hi>Moors,</hi> who from thence did kill our Scouts undiſcovered. In order to their going out, he diſpatches ſeveral Run-aways of the <hi>Moors,</hi> that lived in the Town, to diſcover if any Party was thereabouts to keep Guard. They returned with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that no <hi>Moors</hi> were to be ſeen round about the Country, The unfortunate General believes them, yet he had a preſentiment of his misfortune, and ſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the ſame day of the year, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> had loſt ſix hundred men, maſſacred under their Walls by <hi>Gayland</hi> in perſon. Therefore he was often heard that morning to ſay, Remember, Gentlemen, that this is the Third of <hi>May;</hi> he did diſcover ſome kind of apprehenſion, which one Major <hi>Knightly</hi> laboured to overcome, by offering himſelf to lead out the Party; but he would not be thought to be leſs daring than any man, therefore he adventures out, moſt of his men being fitter to encounter with boughs and ſhrubs than with an Enemy, for they were more armed with Hatchets than with Muskets. He was no ſooner advanced into the Wood, but immediately there appear as many <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hags</hi> as Trees. <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Army of Foot and Horſe it ſeems had marched all night from <hi>Alcazor,</hi> and (as ſome ſay) he had an intention to conclude a Peace. This appearance ſtrook ſuch a fear into our men, that they minded more how to ſave themſelves by flight than to fight; but being about three miles from <hi>Tangier,</hi> and many thouſand Horſe in the Valley, they were all cut off to three men, who recovered the Sea, and hid themſelves in Rocks, until hunger forced them to adventure to <hi>Tangier</hi> again. According to the <hi>Moors</hi> information, ſome of our men did fell their lives at a deer rate; about forty rallied in a place where the Horſe could never come, and began ſuch a deſperate fight with the Foot, that filled the Wood, that as many of their men ended their daies as of ours. Had <hi>Gayland</hi> made uſe of his Victory, and aſſaulted the Town, it had yielded without reſiſtance, the remainder of the Garriſon was ſo aſtoniſhed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99716:6"/>
at this Defeat. Our Horſe, it ſeems, were then Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by an old Souldier that was grown rich, and knew how to ſave his own Pate. Therefore they were not concerned in this fight, but as ſtanders by and lookers on. Had the three Troops advanc'd out of the Lines, they might have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome of our Men.</p>
            <p>My Friend having ended his Relation, we went from the ſight of this unhappy place, unto <hi>Charles</hi> Fort, and to the Decline of a Hill, where he told me that ſome of our men, to the number of three or four encountred with a Troop of Moors, and took from them their Colours, a Diſhonour that had never happened to them before in the ſpace of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years. We continued our walk round the outtermoſt Lines, and there I took notice of the Wiſdom and great Skill of my Lord <hi>Tiveot</hi> in the Art of Fortification: Nothing could be better begun, and were it continued, the City might ſtand in defiance of any Enemy. We had here very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſights into the neigbouring Valleys that are all covered with the natural Tapeſtry of Flowers and green Graſs; for this is the firſt Spring of the Year, the time that the dry Land of <hi>Africa</hi> yields moſt excellent Herbs fit for all uſes. Now when the firſt Rains do fall, I took notice of nothing elſe worthy your knowledge, but of a wild Boar of a ſtrange bigneſs, a little after the Rain had wet the ground, he was turning it up, to ſeek for ſome dry Roots fit for food; he was at ſome diſtance from us, yet I could judge him to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout five or ſix foot high; a deſperate enemy if angered: ſince I have encountered ſome of a leſſer ſize, and found them to be full of Courage and Strength. We ſaw alſo ſome ruined Walls, the ancient Reliques of <hi>Tangier</hi>'s large extent. It reach'd according to all probability, about five or ſix miles in length.</p>
            <p>My Friend did entertain me with many excellent Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſeveral Affairs and Tranſactions of this Place, which I will reſerve for our next Meeting</p>
            <p>I muſt not forget one Story that he affirmed to be true,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99716:7"/>
and which I had afterwards from other perſons; That in the fatal year of 66, the <hi>Portugueſes,</hi> the Dean and Canons of the Cathedral Church of <hi>Tangier</hi> began to rejoyce and to feaſt their Friends in the Moneths of <hi>March</hi> and <hi>April,</hi> and being queſtioned about this unuſual Mirth, they ſaid it was becauſe the time was now come when <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who was reported to have been ſlain near <hi>Alcazar;</hi> ſhould return from his wandring up and down <hi>Africa:</hi> And that he ſhould enter again by the ſame Gate that let him out; it is now ſtopt up, at the Eaſt end of the City joining to the Sea. This old Tale they did believe ſo aſſured, that ſeveral of them began to prepare an Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his ſolemn Reception in their Covent, and did ſhew their Book of Propheſies to confirm this Belief; but either theſe ignorant Fools are miſtaken about the time, or the good Prince hath forgot his way home again; for he hath not yet paid them any Viſit that I could hear of.</p>
            <p>I had the Curioſity to ſee the Mould in the next place: It is thirty yards broad at the top, and it is built about 300, or 350 yards in the Sea: At the end ſome great Guns are planted that command the Harbour, and that carry over the Bay. A Story was told to me by the Serjeant of the guard, that will pleaſe you. About the Moneth of <hi>April</hi> laſt in a dark night, about Eleven of the Clock, the Souldiers upon the Guard heard ſuch fearful Outcries and Shouts, that they were all aſtoniſhed; for it being at ſuch a diſtance from the Town, and ſuch ſtrict Guards being kept at all the Avenues that none could paſs to them, they could not imagin what was the matter, until there appear'd unto them a great Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, attended by leſſer ſhapes, ſome like Men, others like Cats, others like Dogs. The Centry asks <hi>Who's there?</hi> and is anſwered with ſilence; he threatens Death with his Gun; but the Appearances remained unmoveable until the Serjeant with his Guard was allarm'd with the Centry's angry Speeches; and then they began to dance about, and to offer them many Affronts, and to fill the Air with fearful ſhrieks
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99716:7"/>
and Cries a long while. The next morning all the Guard proteſted before the Governour that it was no Illuſion, and that they had been grievouſly diſturbed that night; but none would credit their Relation, until the next night, that there happened ſo violent a ſtorm that 100 yards of the Mould were carried and waſhed away; a thing almoſt incredible: The Waves could never have had that power to deſtroy ſo much Work, had they not been aſſiſted by ſome Infernal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; for the Stones of the Mould are very large; beſides, the upper are linked together with Iron Bars; but the Iron and all the Art of man was not able to reſiſt the fury of the Sea and Wind. That vaſt heap of Stones ſo well diſpoſed and ſetled, was toſt away, and carried at a conſiderable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. I leave it to you, Sir, to judge of the true cauſe of the wonder: You'll give me leave to offer unto you my thoughts, and to tell you how the thing ſtands: This Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident did a little diſcourage the Overſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers of the Mould, but yet they continue with great reſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ution to repair the breaches that the violence of the Sea hath cauſed; and maugre all the Infernal Spirits, to build in the middle of the Sea a ſafe Harbour for our Ships I wiſh the ſucceſs may at laſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer their expectation and endeavours.</p>
            <p>Now you may expect my Judgment of that Place, which I ſend to you freely: It is a moſt pleaſant Seat as is in the world; the Air is pure and refined, the Territory good and fruitful, the Climate very moderate, neither too hot nor too cold, by reaſon of the continual Brizes or the <hi>Eteſiae</hi> Winds that refreſh the Air in the heat of Summer. It were to be deſired that ſuch induſtrious and publick ſpirited per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons did inhabit there as might make an improvement of the goodneſs of the Soil, and of the Conveniencies of the Place. If wine were prohibited, ſo many of our Engliſh Nation had not found here their Graves. Scarce any die here but by Exceſs and Intemperance; ſome having brought themſelves to that capacity of Drinking as that they will make no difficulty to ſwallow above a Quart of ſtrong
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99716:8"/>
               <hi>Nantz</hi> Brandy at one time. We ſee therefore in the moſt of them Death appearing in their faces long before they die. Their inward parts are burnt up with the hot Spirits of their ſtrong Liquors. They ſeem to take pleaſure to deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. If this reigning Vice and ſome others were reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, I doubt not but that City might flouriſh in Engliſh hands, as much as it hath done in former Ages; for it is one of the ancienteſt of the world: it was firſt built by the <hi>Canaanites</hi> that fled from the fury of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſince it hath always been the Chief Place of that Province; the Seat of a Pro-Conſul when <hi>Africa</hi> did ſubmit to the Roman Power. It hath been ſeveral times deſtroyed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the time of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> an Earthquake overthrew the old Walls, and tumbled them far into the Sea, where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main to this day: ſince by the <hi>Saracens</hi> or <hi>Arabs</hi> this City was deſtroyed by the Sword, and all the Inhabitants maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, becauſe it did reſiſt the Power of the Infidels, and by a Sally that was made, had kill'd the Generals Eldeſt Son. It continued next under the Empire of <hi>Morocco</hi> till the year 1523. when the King of <hi>Portugal</hi> attempted to win ſeveral Places upon the <hi>African</hi> Coaſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99716:8"/>
THus have I given yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an account of the City of <hi>Tangier,</hi> which might be made as beneficial to Our King, as any City of his Dominions, if Men did but mind the Publick good, as much as they do their fordid Intereſt.</p>
               <p>We continued here ſome few days, and found a kind En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, eſpecially from the Officers, that are moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging Gentlemen. But as my Lord's buſineſs was not to pitch his Tents in this place, He diſpatcht <hi>C. W.</hi> towards the Emperour, with my ſelf, and another, as well to give notice of His Excellencies arrival, as to procure from him a Paſport, in order to His Journey to <hi>Fez.</hi> We ſet forward with a Flag of Truce in Our Hands, and were met by 20 Horſe about a Mile from the Lines. The Commander came up to Us firſt, and askt from us our buſineſs; We told him by our Interpreter, that His Imperial Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> had ſent an Embaſſador to the great Emperour of <hi>Barbary</hi> his Maſter, a Perſon of a very eminent Quality, and of a moſt Illuſtrious Family, to Treat with him about the Concerns of both Nations. The Captain ſeemed to ſuſpect the truth of what we had ſaid, and asked if we had any Letters; We ſhewed him ſome, but would not part with them: at that He was offended, and lead us about a Mile further behind a Hill where we ſaw 6 Tents erected for Us, and two old Women miſerably deformed, with half a dozen Lancers to Guard them: There was a great Conteſt among them at our firſt appearance; and I thought they had intended to uſe their Weapons. As ſoon as the Commander in Chief, (that was a little behind) was come, all was calm again, We laboured to know the reaſon of their conteſt; and found by our Interpreter, that they were diſputing about a Clauſe of the Law of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet:</hi> both maintaining their different Opinions and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations with much eagerneſs. The one was not ſatisfyed to enjoy his own Fancy, but he was reſolv'd to impoſe it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99716:9"/>
his Comrade, and make him ſubmit unto it by violence. So general is that madneſs amongſt Men, not to allow what Nature cannot refuſe a freedom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Judgment; and to be ſo fond of our Opinions, as to diſturb the Publick Peace, rather than to ſuffer them to be contradicted<hi>:</hi> An unſufferable Pride poſſeſſes their minds. Every petty Coxcomb would erect a Soveraignty in the inviſible world of our Fancies, and would ſee all Men bowing and rendring homage to his Judgement. I'l warrant you if thoſe two naſty Moors had but had a little more breeding, and a little more Authority, they would have been content to have made a Schiſm about Trifles, and to have endangered Mens lives, in the maintainance of their miſtakes. This particular I could not forget, becauſe it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to our own condition at home.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the Commander, whoſe Name was <hi>Zidi Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dala,</hi> was entred into the Tents, and that the Diſpute was over, We ſaw them draw aſide, to conſult what ſhould be done with Us. The Reſolution, as we underſtood, was, that we ſhould remain in cuſtody, until one was ſent to the new Town, to have the Order of <hi>Taffaletta</hi>'s Lientenant that was then there. In the mean while they entertained us with all civility, and preſented to us their greateſt dainties, moiſt Cheeſe, Butter as thick of Goats Hairs, as our Engliſh clay Morter with Straw; ſome muſty Bread, and for our deſert we had ſome wild Honey; a ſad Food to our Engliſh Palats. It is like our Engliſh French Beans, but black. It grows upon ſtalks every where in the Country wild. I never was in ſuch a trouble to eat; for our Interpreter adviſed us not to contemn the Moors kindneſs by a refuſal. We were long at a ſtand, but He began by his Example to ſhew us what We ſhould do: I deceived them all, for with a Cruſt of our Engliſh Bread, that I pull'd out of my Pocket, I kept my Teeth a going. Our Lodging was anſwerable to our Diet. Our Bed was the cold Ground, our covering a pitiful Tent, Our Bedfellows ſtinking Moors; and that which was worſe than all this; it rained all Night upon us, ſo that the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99716:9"/>
                  <hi>Muſketo's,</hi> a venomous Fly did creep under our Cloaths, to ſeek a dry ſhelter, and did ſting us to ſome purpoſe; I wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf again in your good company at the <hi>Kings-Head</hi> at <hi>Charing-Croſs.</hi> We were afraid that our continuance ſhould be longer in this place; for the Moors diſpatches are but ſlow. They obſerve the Spaniſh gravity in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with Chriſtians. An expreſſion of <hi>Grandeur,</hi> that well becomes this miſerable People. About 2 a clock in the afternoon the next Day, We had a few Horſe-men came to us to be our guides to <hi>Salley,</hi> for that was the place unto which we had Order to go. They intended to remain there all Night, becauſe We could not reach <hi>Arzilla</hi> that evening, while it was Day; But our earneſt entreaties prevailed upon them, for we pretended our buſineſs to require haſt, to oblige them to ſet forwards; which accordingly they did 6 in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, about 3 a Clock in the afternoon: as it began to be dusky, we came in ſight of <hi>Arzilla,</hi> a place ſcituate upon the Sea ſhore in a plain Ground; before it there are yet the Ruines of an old Haven, upon which the main Ocean diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charges the fury of its Waves. It yields a pleaſant ſight afar off; for the Turrets of the Wall are Painted with many cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious colours, and many Storks do make their Neſts upon the Battlements. So that it appears to the ignorant Beholder a moſt pleaſant Pallace: but We were never ſo deceived, as when we entred the Gates, and viewed the next day the curioſities of the Town, the greateſt was <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Pallace, and the Caſtle of <hi>Arzilla,</hi> that hath the name of being ſtrong. The Pallace is towards the Sea, and like our old Engliſh Houſes; there is a little Court at the entrance embelliſhed with Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tyles of divers colours: at the left hand, a low Gallery with Rails; before it about 20 Foot long, and to broad, where <hi>Gayland</hi> lay in State to receive the Embaſſadors of Forreign Princes. The good Prince was content it ſeems with a mean Lodging, the apartments of his Officers were not better. That of his Secretaries did look rather like a Swine-keepers Lodge, than a Dwelling for an Officer of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99716:10"/>
State. We were here received with more kindneſs than Pomp. The Governour came to viſit us, and ſent us from his own Table, ſuch Victuals as he himſelf did eat: here I met with ſeveral <hi>Renegadoes,</hi> one <hi>Engliſh</hi> that had been in the Country, He informed us of ſeveral things. One I muſt not omit: Lately when <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Army was routed, and the <hi>Chack</hi> of <hi>Angiers</hi> Son kill'd. The City of <hi>Tetuan</hi> would not ſubmit to <hi>Taffaletta</hi>'s Summons, but ſeemed wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to endure a Siege, but by his Agents in the Town, He did work ſo effectually upon the Inhabitants, that they open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Gates, and yielded themſelves. This good ſucceſs was followed by the reducement of all the Country, which hath a great dependency upon the Mart Town. <hi>Taffaletta</hi> places there a Governour for himſelf, and appoints one of the City to Rule as our Mayors and Bailiffs. This Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour forgetful of his Benefactor, entertain'd ſome correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency with them of <hi>Argiers,</hi> which gave his Maſter cauſe to ſuſpect that he intended a Revolt. <hi>Taffaletta</hi> having learnt that by his Spies diſperſed in all the Cities of <hi>Barbary,</hi> and how he was affected, conceal'd his intentions, and came with a flying Party of Horſe towards <hi>Tetuan.</hi> The Governour hearing of his coming, prepares for his reception, and with a ſmall company goes out about a League from the Town, to meet his Soveraign Prince. He met him at the head of his Army, attended by all his Great Officers: according to his duty, he alighted, and kiſt the Hem of his Garment, a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony that ſignifies as much as the kiſſing our Princes Hands. <hi>Muley Arſheid</hi> commands him to mount upon his Horſe; which being done, He comes cloſe to him, and with his <hi>Stab,</hi> a deſperate Weapon amongſt the <hi>Moors,</hi> He cuts off his Head, takes it by the hindermoſt lock, and there commands all his Army to paſs by, ſhewing and ſhaking the Head now and then at ſuch as he ſuſpected of unconſtancy and unfaithfulnes. This is a ſign of his great reſolution and courage. The ſight of this Head did not a little terrify the reſt of his <hi>Grandees,</hi> who are become wonderfully faithful to his Intereſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99716:10"/>
Immediately after this Execution He goes to <hi>Tetuan,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints the People with the Traitors Guilt, and he wanted not the applauſes of the fawning <hi>Moors,</hi> that are for him who hath the greateſt Power. <hi>Taffaletta</hi> places over the City another Governour, a Perſon moſt intimate with Him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was a place of great Importance: He likewiſe incurs his diſpleaſure by ſome misfortune, and ended his days ſoon after his Predeceſſour, in this manner. A Gentleman ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied only by two luſty <hi>Blacks,</hi> comes to <hi>Tetuan,</hi> and asks for the Governour; the People ſhew him a little Hill, where he was gone to take the Air: thither He comes with all ſpeed, and falutes the Governour, delivering to him ſome Letters from the <hi>Sultan;</hi> which were received with all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Joy. The poor Governour not thinking that his death was ſo nigh at hand; He invites the Gentleman to his Houſe, and did not ſo much as dream of the Miſchief prepared for him. All this while the other keeps his deſign ſecret, and being entred with the Governour into the Houſe, and ſat down upon Carpets, as the manner of that Country is; He diſcourſed with him about ſeveral Affairs; and at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, when he ſaw his opportunity, He pulls out of his Pocket a Sentence of Death Signed by <hi>Taffaletta,</hi> which he bid the Governour read. Theſe unwelcome Lines did ſtrike ſuch an amazement into his Mind, that he became unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. The other commanded his <hi>Blacks,</hi> that had been care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to follow him to the Chamber door, to come in, and do their Office. They preſently take the Cord that they had prepared on purpoſe; and without delay, fall upon him. The miſerable Governour ſeeing no remedie, begs on his knees the ſavour to be Strangled with the Shaſh about his Middle. That ſatisfaction was granted unto him Thus he that was intimate with his Prince, and that did ſlatter himſelf in his Proſperity, ended his days when he leaſt ſuſpected it The Gentleman goes next into the Streets of the City with his naked <hi>Cimeter,</hi> and cauſes it to be Proclaimed by his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants:
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99716:11"/>
That the Prince, for juſt cauſe, had commanded the Governour to be put to death; and that he was appointed in his ſtead to Rule in that City, and that if any would op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe his Reception, that he ſhould appear. The Citizens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the Fact, curſed the dead Governour, and received the new with all Honour. An infallible ſign of the Peoples great Reſpect and Submiſſion to their Princes Judgement and Actions, That none did dare to ſearch into his Proceedings, or to examine the Juſtice of his commands. This expreſſes alſo his great confidence and truſt that he repoſes upon his Peoples Obedience. To diſpoſe in ſuch an abſolute manner of their Lives and Fortunes; and in ſuch a powerful City, to think to bring to paſs ſuch an unexpected change by ſuch weak Agents in a moment. He could never have ventured to give ſuch a Commiſſion, had he not been aſſured of the <hi>Moors</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention to his Pleaſure. I have ſince heard at <hi>Fez,</hi> that there is a Cloud that hangs over this Governour of <hi>Tetuan</hi> alſo, which may have the ſame effect upon him, as upon the former It is certain, <hi>Taffaletta</hi> removes, deſtroys, ſtrangles, and baniſhes all that he ſuſpects in the leaſt.</p>
               <p>We remained one Night in <hi>Arzilla,</hi> and the next Day we Journeyed through the Country called <hi>Elfas,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the Plow Land;</hi> It reaches as far as one can diſcover from <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giers</hi> a great number of little Hills do appear, upon which, and in the Valleys the beſt Corn of <hi>Africa</hi> doth grow. It was the cuſtom of the <hi>Moors</hi> in <hi>Gayland</hi>'s time, to repair thither from all parts to Plow and Sow, and every one had a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Portion of Land appointed for him, which he Manured, and at the Harveſt he payed only the tenth part to the King, unto whom all the Land belongs. It is a very fruitful Soil in that part, and yields a great increaſe, eſpecially of Wheat In our Journey this day, which was the moſt pleaſant that we ever had we met with ſome few Tents, and out of one came forth a little dirty Rogue about 12 years old, curſing us becauſe we were Chriſtians; He ſpoke ſo much <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99716:11"/>
to name us <hi>Peras Chriſtianos,</hi> you Chriſtian Dogs. This People is bred up with a prejudice againſt Us, and taught from their Cradle to abhor our Religion. It is the Divels policy to keep them thus in their Ignorance, by giving them in their tender years an inveterate hatred of the Truth, and its Profeſſours, unto which their Reaſon might otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them, when they attain to an age of diſcretion, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
               <p>We arrived that night at <hi>Alcazar, Gayland</hi>'s unhappy City, where he was overcome, and where four of his Wives were taken for the Conqueror's uſe: It is an ancient City, ſuch as the moſt of that Country are; pitiful for the Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: It hath a few Streets that are ſtraight as a Line at both ends. There are Gates joining to the Houſes, I conceive, to defend them from wild Beaſts; for it is not poſſible to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them from Men; the Gates that are at the end of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Street are like our good great Barn Doors, ſo old that they can ſcarce hang upon the Hinges. This is that Famous City where three Kings were kill'd in a day, and the Arch Rebel of <hi>Ireland, Stukely,</hi> created by the Pope, Earl of <hi>Wexford,</hi> and Marquiſs of <hi>Leinſter,</hi> died alſo, with thoſe Troops that were intended for the diſturbance of Qu. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Dominions: But here Divine Juſtice overtook them, and prevented their bloody Deſigns. We had the Governours Houſe for our Lodging; for it is the Cuſtom in all thoſe Countries to repair to the Houſe of the Chief Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Place, who is prepared for your Entertainment; having, as all the Eaſtern People, a Gueſt-Chamber or Room to keep Strangers dry. Every one brings his own Proviſion with him. There are no publick Houſes of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, or Inns; but he that is a man of any eſteem, is bound to receive ſtrangers. Now the Cuſtom is amongſt the <hi>Arabs</hi> that live in Tents, That when a Stranger comes, and deſires to be received, he ſtands at a diſtance over againſt the Principal Tent praying to <hi>Mahomet:</hi> The Maſter when he ſees him, either ſends for him, or goes himſelf to fetch
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99716:12"/>
him in for <hi>Mah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>met</hi>'s ſake, whether he be poor or rich; according to the cuſtom of the Ancient Fathers, who were thus hoſpitable to Paſſengers.</p>
               <p>We found here very much Civility, when our Buſineſs was known and divulged, many perſons of quality flock'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to bid us welcome; for this Country deſires nothing more earneſtly than to entertain a good correſpondency with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for whom, above all Nations, they have a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular kindneſs and a great eſteem, becauſe their Slaves are ſo well treated amongſt us, and becauſe we bow not to Images, which they abhor. Amongſt thoſe that did viſit us while we were at Supper, a famous Negromancer came in to ſee us, and bid us be of good chear, and that he deſired to ſhew his reſpect to us by a Dance and Muſick. He had under his Arm a long Inſtrument with a Wire inſtead of a String, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he plaid moſt dexterouſly. He had no ſooner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, but in ſteps an ill ſhap'd Rogue as black as the Devil, followed by a furious Goat and a Dog; theſe three began the Dance, the Goat and Dog ſtriking the Ground accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſound of the Inſtrument. The Sport had been pleaſant, had we not been informed by a Stander by that theſe ſhapes were not real, but that they were Devils or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Spirits that did thus appear at his Command. This Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy did make us deſire that the Paſtime would end a little ſooner than otherwiſe we would have done. The Negro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer perceived it; therefore he concluded; and all theſe Appearances vaniſh'd to our Eyes, the Door being then ſhut, leaving ſuch a horrible Stench as made us all riſe to ſeek the open Air to breath; Which the Negromancer laboured to excuſe, telling us we had affronted his Devils, by expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a Diſlike of their Kindneſs, and therefore we might thank our ſelves if they had left ſuch an ill Sent to puniſh our Contempt: We told him by our Interpreter, that we did not deſire ſuch Entertainment, and that the Devils Company was never grateful to us. This Accident made us fall to our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99716:12"/>
Prayers, and be more devout than otherwiſe we ſhould have been: We afterwards inquired what this Fellow was; ſome told us, that his Name was <hi>Zidi Lamed,</hi> a man highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed amongſt the <hi>Moors</hi> becauſe of his Art in Negro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancy, and his Acquaintance with Familiar Spirits, by which he knows the News of all the world, and foretels ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to the People which they are deſirous enough to know; ſo that he is conſulted as an Oracle in all urgent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. There are many that ſtudy the Black Art, but this man was the moſt eminent. As he went from us, he let fall ſome threatning words, which we did not underſtand till the next day, that we all fell from our Horſes and bruiſed our ſelves. That night we forgot not to ſay our Prayers, and to recommend our ſelves to Gods Protection. And aſſoon as it was day we departed towards <hi>Saley,</hi> and that night we came to the Mountain called <hi>Iſtibel,</hi> where one <hi>Beleif</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, as being his Inheritance; I ſhould be too tedious to write every Accident that happened to us in the way. Our next Stage was <hi>Sarſar</hi> upon the River <hi>Sbom,</hi> where one of our Guides, a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Renegado ſhewed me the Place where a great Battel had been fought between <hi>Gayland</hi> and <hi>Ham del Hag,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Bembouqua;</hi> in which he told me he did fight for <hi>Gayland,</hi> and was preſent during the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter. The two Princes were at variance for their Limits, which cauſed them to expoſe the Lives of their Subjects, and to give many Battels: this that was fought upon the Banks of the River <hi>Sbow,</hi> was a bloudy one, and fatal to <hi>Bembou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua</hi>'s Intereſt through his own eagerneſs; for he being with his Horſe and Foot beyond the River, ventured over to charge the Enemy; <hi>Gayland</hi> keeping his men cloſe, expecting his Coming, at laſt he gave ſuch a furious Onſet, that the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>'s men gave back with much loſs; notwithſtanding the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals Courage rallies them and brings them on again; here Victory was long uncertain; ſometimes one Party flies, ſometimes the other; and had it not been for a freſh Supply of Men led on by <hi>Gayland</hi>'s ſecond Brother, which came at
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99716:13"/>
that moment, he had loſt the Day; but his Number increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with this unexpected Recruit, and by conſequence, his mens hearts being thereby filled with new Courage, he had not much difficulty to overcome his Enemies, who had at their Retreat two ſorts of Enemies to fight withal, <hi>Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s men, who purſued with all Fury behind, and a deep River before; for the Bridge over which <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbouqua</hi> ſaved himſelf was broken down. Many were killed that day, but more were drowned, in all of the Saint's men about 5000 ſtout Souldiers. This Succeſs of <hi>Gayland</hi> cauſed many of the Saints Subjects to revolt to him, and to ſet up his Banner in their ſeveral Juriſdictions: So that he became by this Battel a moſt powerful Prince, very dreadful to his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. This happened in the Year 1663.</p>
               <p>By the way as we paſſed, we had a ſight of ſeveral <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Garriſons upon the Sea-ſide: <hi>Larache,</hi> where <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Power received a very great check by a handful of <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who made ſuch a brisk Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y upon them, that they kill'd a good number of his Men, took <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Brother, and hang'd him up upon their Walls: A bold Action! that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them odious to the Country and to <hi>Gayland;</hi> ſo that he never would have any peace with them.</p>
               <p>The next is <hi>Mammora,</hi> a noted place in <hi>Spain;</hi> for there they baniſh the malefactors. As we were over againſt this Gariſon, our Company being advanced a little before, there happened an Accident that ſcar'd me more than it hurt me, a Horſeman having ſpoken with our Guides, who told him our buſineſs, and who we were, came up to me, having but one Moor with me, and brandiſh'd his Lance as he rid tilt at me; I underſtood not his meaning, and thought he had intended Miſchief, yet I was afraid to diſcover my Fear, and therefore I would not put myſelf upon a poſture of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence till I felt his Weapon; but I was ſurpriz'd, when in ſtead of a Blow with his Lance, which I expected, ſeeing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99716:13"/>
him gallopping at me, he moſt dexterouſly turn'd the Point, and laid the other end upon the Pommel of my Saddle; a great expreſſion of Civility and Kindneſs amongſt them, as I underſtood by our Interpreter; reſigning by that Action, the Weapon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> into the hands of him whom they treat in that manner: When I ſaw his Intentions were not evil, I ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him according to our faſhion: after a little Diſcourſe with the Moor, he went his way, and I made up to my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
               <p>We came through the Country of <hi>Elhalat,</hi> a Plain Ground, ſo named from that Tribe that dwells there, and within three days we arrived at <hi>Saley:</hi> The City ſtands very pleaſantly; it is divided into two parts, a River paſſing in the middle of the City. It is two Miles about, having a very ſtrong Caſtle at one end, with a ſcurvy Harbour for Ships before it. We were led directly to the Governours Houſe, where we met with a kind entertainment, eſpecially <hi>C. W.</hi> who was well known to the Town. Here we found many <hi>Engliſh</hi> Slaves, taken in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Bottoms by the Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates of this place; ſome were newly brought in. We gave them all the aſſiſtance our Purſes or Favour could afford, and put them in ſome hopes to obtain their Freedom, if my Lord was ſo happy as to obtain a firm Peace, a joyful news to thoſe poor wretches, that had left all hopes of returning home to their beloved Soil.</p>
               <p>Here we remained ſome days, viewing the ancient Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of the Town, that is poſſeſſed by the <hi>Arabs.</hi> And here we took notice of the miſerable condition of the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> There are a great number of them in the Country round about, diſperſed up and down. The <hi>Arabians</hi> are their Lords, having Power of Life and Death over them. Each <hi>Arab</hi> hath his particular Servants that he ſends to Till his Ground, and from him requires ſo much Tribute either in Corn or Money every year. Sometimes he rides about
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99716:14"/>
to view his Territories, and then his Tenants are bound to provide him with all neceſſaries: Beſides, he takes from them what he pleaſes, and Sells them and their Family, and diſpoſes the poor <hi>Brabbers</hi> as he liſts. For as the <hi>Arabians</hi> are entred into the Country by way of Conqueſt, they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly behave themſelves there as Conquerors, treating the Inhabitants as Slaves and Captives. But at the death of the laſt King, they freed themſelves from the <hi>Arabian</hi> Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and under the Conduct of ſeveral Princes did ſubdue the <hi>Arabians</hi> themſelves. <hi>Gayland, Bembouqua,</hi> and ſeveral others, had many ſucceſsful Battles with the <hi>Arabs,</hi> their Maſters, for near Twenty years; and becauſe of ſome Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions amongſt them, and that their Lawful Prince was ſlain, they could not recover their former Eſtate, until <hi>Taffaletta</hi>'s late Victories over the <hi>Barbarians, Gayland,</hi> and the reſt. When the Governour of this place was acquainted with Our buſineſs, He freely gave us a Paſs through his Government, for he commands much of the Country round about almoſt as far as <hi>Fez;</hi> unto which City, We ſet forward next through a Tribe of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> called <hi>Mouktar;</hi> and by the way we deſired to know the meaning of ſeveral Pillars and Monuments; Our Guards told us, that they were ſet up by the Army of the <hi>Arabians</hi> that came from the Eaſt, when they over ran this Country, in memory of ſome ſignal Battles given in thoſe places againſt the Inhabitants; for as amongſt the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> they give Names to ſeveral places, according to the accidents that happen there. We thus paſt without any moleſtation, being ſometimes obliged to ſhew our Paſport to the Chief Men. As we were come about 10 Leagues on this ſide of <hi>Fez;</hi> We paſt through a delicate Champaign Ground, over fruitful for ſuch lazy Inhabitants as the <hi>Moors.</hi> In a pleaſant Valley about 2 Leagues further, We paſſed by above a thouſand Tents, diſtinguiſht by their ſeveral Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, which were ſeparated at ſome convenient diſtance, round about many thouſand head of Cattle were a feeding. Now theſe that live in Tents are the <hi>Arabs,</hi> the People that came
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99716:14"/>
from <hi>Arabia</hi> by the ſollicitation of the ancient <hi>Sultan</hi> of <hi>Morocco,</hi> who made uſe of their aſſiſtance to recover his Dominions from an Uſurper, that in his abſence had revolted from him; ſince they have over-ſpread all this Country: and as their manner is, they live in Tents, and as the <hi>Nomades</hi> remove from place to place with all their Subſtance. They are diſtinguiſhed into ſeveral great Tribes, as the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe Brethren they are: for they are the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, Aagarens,</hi> or <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> or the Poſterity of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> the Son of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Their manner of living may be a very good Commentary to ſeveral Paſſages of the Old Teſtament. The chief Tribes are named <hi>Heldauquella, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>deſees, Spenet, Elholot, Mouktar, Shregga, Hiaina, Soubba, Dama, Themſna, Hel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eela, Elanyad,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe are divided into Families, Governed by the firſt born, who hath a jurisdiction over the ſeveral Members. They have all a dependency upon him, and received from him their livelihood. He is their Captain in War, their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Peace, their Judge when any difference ariſes in his Precinct. Therefore, all their Tents do keep cloſe to him; His Tent is planted Weſterly, being bigger and handſomer than the reſt: then the others are erected on both Hands, as a half Moon, open towards the Eaſt, aſwel that they might ſalute the Riſing Sun, for whom they have a great Reverence, as that they might look towards <hi>Mecha,</hi> the place of <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi>'s Birth, for which alſo they have a particular Devotion. In the middle of the Tents, there is one which is appointed for their Meeting to Prayer. This Barbarous People have that good Inſtinct to ſet apart a place for the Worſhip of God. Where there are many hundred Tents together, a Prieſt alſo, had in great eſteem amongſt them, is ſet a part for that Service; unto ſome they appoint 100 Dollers, to ſome more, to others leſs, according to their Number. His Office is to Read Prayers 5 times a day, unto which he calls the People, ſtanding at the Door of the Tent with his <hi>Alla illa Mahomet reſul all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99716:15"/>
and many other expreſſions of Humility and Devotion: His Office alſo is to teach the Children to Read and Write <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick,</hi> and to inſtruct them in the Law of <hi>Mahomet.</hi> An excellent Cuſtom, but ill applyed. By that means, theſe <hi>Talouts,</hi> for that is their names, do render themſelves ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, and do train up their Children in awe and reſpect of their Order, and of Religion, Imprinting in their tender minds thoſe Impreſſions, as may make them for ever faithful to <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and his Intereſt. That is the cauſe that every one is ſo Devout, and that Prophaneſs finds ſuch little enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment amongſt them. It were to be wiſht that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy would practice the ſame Cuſtom, and take into their tuition the Children of their ſeveral Pariſhes; We might then hope that the next Generation of Men would be leſs Atheiſtical and Vitious, and more Devoted to the Service of God, and their Prince. Their conſtant Preaching ſhould not hinder the Catechizing of Youth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I am ſure that would be the means to expel Ignorance which reigns in Cities, and Country. It would alſo be the means to ſettle their Intereſt in the Kingdom, and to raiſe their Holy Order in the eſteem and favour of the People, from whence (it is unhappily fallen by their own miſcarriages. Beſides, theſe ordinary ſort of Prieſts, there are others called <hi>Elftees,</hi> Itinerary Preachers, who are eſteemed Learned in the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Law; theſe do upon the Solemn Days, and when they are required, aſcend up into a Pulpit, and there they Expound a Text of the <hi>Alcoran.</hi> It is wonderful to ſee the Veneration, and the reſpect that is paid to theſe Men. There is nothing too precious for them, no company too Honourable. They are lookt upon as ſo many Gods amongſt the People, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with the greateſt expreſſions of love and kindneſs. I did often wiſh that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Clergy were as happy as theſe Men. But that may be deſired, but never expected in our days.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99716:15"/>
Several other ſorts there are; ſome called <hi>Hages,</hi> or <hi>Saints;</hi> they are thoſe that have viſited <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Tomb. Of their other Orders ſeveral have written. Now the chief of every Family appoints a <hi>Thaloub,</hi> to inſtruct his People, and Pray for them. If any difference ariſes between them, or any injury be done, they come before Him: His Sentence is a Law to them; ſo great is the priviledge of the firſt born. They have no Judges, but in Cities: Thoſe that live in Tents, do ſubmit to the pleaſure of their Chieftain. I ſaw a Fellow, that in his anger had ſtab'd his Comerade in the Belly; the Wound was not ſo Mortal, but he came immediately before the chief of the Family; who preſently ordred him to be ſent for, to pay for his Cure, and 10 Dollers beſides; and then taking a ſound Stick, commanded him to lie upon his Belly; which was immediately done, then he gave him 10 blowes upon his Breech. The Fellow having receiv'd his Puniſhment, made a profound Reverence, and ſeemed to be as contented as ever, only for his 10 Dollers; He deſired his Party to compound with him. Another had ſtollen a Hen from a <hi>Thaloub,</hi> with ſome other trifles: the crime being known, He was ſent for, and all the ſtollen Goods, that weighed about 20 Pounds, were hung at his Ears, through which wide holes were made, and he condemned to ſtand thus at the entry of their <hi>Moſque;</hi> or Tent conſecrated to Prayer. I have ſeen many other Puniſhments of the like nature inflicted. Their ordinary is the <hi>Baſtinado</hi> for ſmall offences; <hi>Empalling</hi> for grievous; and for ſome they Burn, they Hang, Strangle, and Poyſon. There is another manner of Execution very ſtrange; they put a Fellow naked, only ſomthing about his middle to hide the Privity, which they can never abide to behold. They ſhackle his Feet, ſo that he may only go and then they let looſe upon him the Boys and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who with their ſharp Canes, do make him bleed to death, pricking him, till he gives up the Ghoſt: this is the moſt cruel death practiſed amongſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99716:16"/>
One thing I cannot forget of their Cuſtoms. If any kills another, the next Brother or the next Kinſman is bound to ſeek the Murderer out, and to kill him where ever he meets him; Beſides, they ſwear to maintain their Captains, and to die in their Quarrels. So that one Company of Tents many times do fall out with another. For they are diſpoſed of in the Country of ſo many little Villages, making the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of a Town.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Arabs,</hi> by what I have ſaid, you may perceive that they hate the Government of <hi>Barbary,</hi> and love a free Life. Since the laſt Emperour of <hi>Morocco</hi> that was Maſſacred by his Servants, never any had any rule over them, but they maintained a kind of an <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> amongſt themſelves, until <hi>Muley Arſheid</hi> caſt himſelf into their Protection, when he fled from his elder Brother <hi>Muley Mehammed.</hi> He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf ſo bravely, and did ingratiate himſelf ſo cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly with them, that they made him firſt their General, or Great <hi>Moukadem.</hi> In which Imployment he had won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Succeſs againſt the Eaſt <hi>Arabs:</hi> a People that cannot endure the Weſt. After he led them againſt his elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and enriched many of them with Plunder and Spoil. That made them proceed to this Election, in which he was ſo happy, that all conſented to make him their King or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. This was his firſt riſe after the death of his elder Brother, that he took Priſoner, and then kill'd. The chief of the Kingdom of <hi>Taffaletta</hi> made him alſo their Soveraign Prince. He hath a younger Brother named <hi>Muley Zidan,</hi> and that he might oblige the People to a greater obedience, and more fidelity, he hath given out, that he is of the Race of their Prophet <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and that acording to that Law none ought to Command in Chief, but one lineally deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from <hi>Mahomet.</hi> This Perſwaſion prevails much upon the ſuperſtitious <hi>Moors,</hi> and diſables them from reſiſting or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing his proceedings, for fear of their Prophet, makes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99716:16"/>
them revolt from their former Governours, and ſubmit to his Dominion. He hath Conquered all <hi>Gayland</hi>'s Country, and the Territories of <hi>Bembouqua,</hi> called <hi>Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Mehamed, Boubquer del <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ago,</hi> the King of <hi>Morocco,</hi> who had been an Uſurper. The Kingdom of <hi>Sous,</hi> the Countries where theſe Tribes do dwell, <hi>Themſna, Heldedla, Moukter, Hiania, Widlobar, Elangad, Heldouquella, Uleidezin, Dama,</hi> and many more; all making up 43 Tribes, with the Country of <hi>Hel Iſhbel:</hi> All theſe Kingdoms and Places do acknowledge him for their Prince. Only ſome Petty Lords of the Craggy Mountains do reſiſt his Power. Againſt theſe he is now marched with his Army, and as we hear, hath reduced ſome to Obedience, having executed great Numbers of them in a cruel manner<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to terrifie the reſt. Theſe are <hi>Barbari,</hi> the ancient Inhabitants of that Country, who have been forced to ſubmit to the yoke of the <hi>Arabians;</hi> yet in theſe latter days they were become Maſters over them, and did uſe them very hardly when their laſt Emperour was kill'd; for then they fell into Diviſions. <hi>Alcaide Iſſa,</hi> a great man amongſt them, commanded the chief of their Tribes: Next was <hi>Zidi Douckag,</hi> with <hi>Zidi Boumhedi.</hi> All three had under them <hi>Sheirs,</hi> Governors of Tribes, that they had ingaged in their Parties; but when they fell out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, <hi>Bembouqua</hi> that commanded the great Country called <hi>Heliſhbel</hi> and <hi>Fez,</hi> where the <hi>Barbarians</hi> do live, took the advantage, and made War upon the <hi>Arabians,</hi> and reduced them to Obedience, uſing them in the ſame manner as they did before his People, as ſo many Slaves; which made them put themſelves more willingly under one Head, that by his means they might free themſelves from the <hi>Barbarian</hi> Bondage. The Caſe here is much like that of the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> by <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s means they conquered <hi>Canaan,</hi> and did domineer over the Inhabitants; but thoſe of the Sea Coaſt could not be driven out: when therefore they ſaw an opportunity, they did revenge themſelves upon the Poſterity of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> until <hi>Iſrael</hi> made <hi>Saul</hi> their King,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99716:17"/>
and after him <hi>David;</hi> then they returned to their former Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the Inhabitants &amp; the Country round. Thus is it with their Brethren the <hi>Arabs;</hi> they conquered all this Country, and made the Inhabitants bear the Yoke; but ſometimes thoſe that live in ſtrong Places and high Mountains, do revolt from them, and give them no little diſturbance, as they have done in theſe late years under ſeveral great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. A memorable Battel was given about <hi>Saley</hi> between them, where ten or twelve thouſand <hi>Arabians</hi> were killed, and their Families and Cattel taken by <hi>Bembouqua</hi> at the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Widlobar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now theſe <hi>Arabians</hi> do never mingle themſelves with the <hi>Brabbers,</hi> thinking themſelves an abler Generation of men; neither doth one Tribe mix with another: they obſerve in that the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> At the Diviſion of the Land, they had for every Tribe a parcel of Ground appointed, in which they live up and down in their Tents, never going with their Cattel out of their own Limits, unleſs ſome urgent occaſion calls them; as when they fight: Then all the Tribes join, and form an Army: over which they elect a General. Now every Tribe keeps a Record of all the Members of Perſons that do belong unto it, and therefore every one is able to give an account of his Anceſtor; All the Royal Blood pretends to be come from <hi>Haly, Mahomet</hi>'s Son in Law. The <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians</hi> acknowledge none other for Prince, but he that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be thus deſcended. <hi>Taffaletta</hi> or <hi>Muley Arſheid</hi> is ſo; his Anceſtors have long commanded in the Kingdom of <hi>Taffalet,</hi> being entred there with the Conqueſt of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>In our Journey to <hi>Fez,</hi> we met with many thouſand <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs</hi> removing with their Subſtance from place to place, and they were the Tribes of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>laidezin Dama Saubba,</hi> amongſt whom we lodged one night; and were invited by one of the <hi>Sheirs</hi> to Supper: We had a Table ſpread with all the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99716:17"/>
of that Country, and very good Water to drink, mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a ſweet Stuff much like our Mead. Our Seats were Carpets, our Table the Ground. When we came at the Gate of <hi>Fez,</hi> we were commanded to light off of our Horſes, becauſe no Chriſtian is to ride on a Horſe in that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. You may expect an account of this City; but that I reſerve for ſome other time, when I can write to you. I think this Letter is long enough to weary your Patience. At our Arrival, we found <hi>Taffaletta</hi> gone with his Army againſt ſome <hi>Barbarians</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Sous,</hi> beyond <hi>Morocco:</hi> And it is reported here that he hath obtained a great Victory over a conſiderable Number of them, and that the reſt are retreated into the Mountains. We hear that he will be here within a few Moneths, and then we hope to have our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches: Some are ſent to acquaint him with the Honour our King hath done him, to ſend him a Perſon ſo eminent in our Nation, and of that great Wiſdom. In the mean while, we have here a Civil entertainment, and have liberty to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert our ſelves in hunting the Wild Boar with ſome Perſons of Quality in this Place, who love the Sport, but make no uſe of the Fleſh. I have ſeen abundance of rare things in this City; for it is a very ſumptuous one, becauſe of the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Marble that are here.</p>
               <p>You ſee, Sir, that I have leiſure to write a long Letter; it is to ſatisfie your Curioſity. I ſend it to you by one that goes from hence to <hi>Tangier,</hi> and there my Friend hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to take care of any thing that I ſhall ſend. God keep you, and ſend us a happy Meeting.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours to Command, <hi>S. L.</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>Fez, <date>
                        <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1. 1669.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:99716:18"/>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99716:18"/>
            <head>A Brief Account of the Native Commodities of <hi>AFRICA.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Frica</hi> yields moſt excellent things fit for the uſe of man: The Ground may diſpute in Fruitfulneſs with any part of <hi>Europe:</hi> it only wants Rain to moderate the heat of the Climate; when the ſhowers come, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where green Herbs appear amongſt the drieſt Sand. Here are excellent Simples ſit for Phyſick. It hath often been obſerved that many Creatures when offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by their Enemy, and wounded, have ſought after ſome of theſe Herbs that are proper to cure and heal them; Gods Providence hath therefore planted that part of the world with ſuch good and healing Roots as might oppoſe the Malice, and prevent the Miſchiefs of Venomous Creatures, whereof here are a great number, eſpecially in the Land; and in the Woods there are great Numbers of Scorpions as black as a Coal, Serpents that caſt themſelves from Trees and ſurprize and wound the unwary Paſſenger. Here are venomous Aſpes, whoſe leaſt touch brings preſent death, let it be never ſo ſmall; for it conveys its Poiſon ſecretly into the Veins, through the leaſt wound, and that infects the next bloud; thus the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection ſpreads by degrees until it reaches the heart. Here are many Baſilisks; a dreadful Creature, that kills by the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99716:19"/>
infection of the Air. There is alſo another kind that cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a preſent drineſs in the Palate aſſoon as it hath wounded the man, and therefore called by the Ancients <hi>Dipſas.</hi> The Inhabitants ſpeak of a new ſort of Creature that they ſee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every Year; for when all the Creatures do come to the freſh Springs and Fountains, the heat carries them to unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Copulation, and from theſe extraordinary Conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do proceed Monſters that are of ſeveral Species, which have not the power to propagate or to increaſe. Beyond the City of <hi>Fez</hi> there is a great Wilderneſs full of wild Beaſts and Fowls. The <hi>Arabs</hi> do live in all the fruitful places; but in the Land nothing is to be ſeen but Mountains of Sand, that are very dreadful in a ſtorm of Wind, becauſe it carries and tranſports them from place to place, and buries the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger under the weight of it alive. The Commodities of this Countrey are very many; it were a happy thing to have a Prince there that did command all the Land, and that were a Lover of Trade; then <hi>Carovans</hi> might go ſafe from place to place without fear of robbing: But the nature of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabs</hi> inclines them to thieving and violence; ſo that although one ſhould have a Paſport from the Prince, it is a great ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, if you be not provided with a good Guard, that you will be ſet upon by theſe Rogues, who are notwithſtanding, in their eſteem, the beſt Gentlemen, and the nobleſt in the World. The chief Commodities are Hides, they kill as many wild Bulls and Cows in the Land, as they of the <hi>Eaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Indies</hi> do in their Plantations. Beſides Goat-skins, <hi>Marok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Leather, that are excellent, here is great ſtore of Honey; the Bees do increaſe in the Woods and Mountains, and as there are excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Flowers that grow in all the Valleys, ſo naturally the Country is full of Bees and Wax. There is alſo a kind of Silk Stuffe that is made by the Inhabitants of the Sea-ſhore, of the Bark of Trees. Here is alſo Raw Silk; the Countrey breeds ſilk-Worms in great abundance about <hi>Fez</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rocco.</hi> Here are many other things uſeful to the life of man,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99716:19"/>
if Peace were eſtabliſhed in the Country, and with our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then we might fetch from <hi>Guiny,</hi> and the <hi>Negro's</hi> Country, the rich commoditie of Gold duſt.</p>
            <p>Now every Month ſome of the <hi>Blacks</hi> do adventure to <hi>Fez,</hi> with Camels loaden with that ſuperfluous Earth, of which they have too much, and carry back other trifles that are eſteemed amongſt them. Some ſay that the Sun hath burnt the Sand of the Wilderneſs in ſome places, and that it is become perfect Gold. It is certain, that in the Sandy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts the <hi>Blacks</hi> do gather up Gold; This Gold is the beſt in the World, it is as pliable almoſt as Paper, and doth not ſo eaſily conſume and waſte. If ſome would adventure in the Land, to ſearch out the Country, and bring a juſt and a true Report, he might diſcover many things which our Traders might improve to their advantage. In the Wilderneſs there are great ſtore of wild Aſſes, Horſes, Lions, Jaccals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is wonderful of this laſt, that ſmells a dead Carkaſe many Miles; and towards the Night, they run howling out of their Dens and Caves in great numbers right to the place where lies their Prey. The Lions and Leopards, and other furious Creatures are preſently awakened with the noiſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they follow them always. A Jaccal is a kind of a Fox, bigger and longer, juſt of the ſame ſhape, but for the moſt part of a blackiſh Gray, as high as a good Maſtiff Dog. In the Night they ſurround the Tents of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> and if they meet any diſ-armed, he ſerves to ſatisfie their hunger; for then ſuch a company do over power him, that he is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and torn in pieces in a moment. Here are alſo many Apes and Baboons. The Apes do dwell in Forreſts and Woods on the tops of Trees: Sometimes they venture down in the Valleys in Troops, 6 or 7 hundred at a time, and do a conſiderable execution upon the poor Corn. Many are undone by this ſcurvy Vermin. They never ſuſpect the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Creature, but preſently ſave themſelves by ſlight at the leaſt diſcovery or appearance of Man or Beaſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It is remarkable, what hath been obſerved of them, that he that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99716:20"/>
comes firſt to a Tree, he skips, and ſeizes upon a bow, which he labours to bend to the Ground, then all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions do follow, and run upon the Tree over his Back that comes firſt to the place. Here are many ſtrange Inſects, and Birds of divers colours. There is one remarkable, that our <hi>Engliſh</hi> call a <hi>Bee eater;</hi> It is Red, Blew, White, Yellow, Green, and very handſomely painted with divers colours: It appears in the Months of <hi>April, May, June, July,</hi> the hotteſt Months of the Year. They purſue the ſwarms of Bees, and devour them, and have a cry much like a Frogg. They dwell in the Land during the Rains, and come to the Sea-coaſt in Summer &amp; Spring. Here are alſo excellent Roots, that are brought from the Eaſt and Weſt <hi>Indies</hi> to us, ſuch as do fill the Shops of our Druggiſts. Were that Country in the hands of an ingenious and laborious People; it is not to be doubted, but that it would furniſh the reſt of the World with excellent Productions: But ſince the Conqueſt of the Country by the <hi>Arabs,</hi> War and Oppreſſions have hindred the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants from the improvement of their Soil.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. 1. Line 5. for requeſt, read <hi>expect.</hi> p. 4. l. 22. for race, r. <hi>far.</hi> p. 5. l 16. for from r. <hi>into</hi> p. 7. l. 18. for twelve, r. <hi>ſixteen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
